好吧，我想我们可以开始了，现在可以开始了欢迎回到13号
all right I guess we can get we can get
started now welcome back it's the 13th
上次我们停下来谈话时的浓缩物质课程演讲
lecture of the condensed matter course
when last we left off we were talking
关于散射的基本实验是，您有一些样品，在
about scattering the basic experiment is
you have some sample you have a wave at
一些波矢量K，您将其发送到样本中，然后散开
some wave vector K that you send into
the sample and then it's scattered off
到一些波向量K Prime上，并测量多少
to some wave vector K Prime and by
measuring how much and in what
您有分散的方向，您可以推断出什么
directions you have scattering you're
able to deduce something about what's
实际上，在样本中，我们对这些类型的
actually in the sample a couple of
things that we know about these type of
首先进行散射实验，以便从k到k进行散射
scattering experiments first of all in
order to get scattering from k to k
素数必须有K减去K素数等于倒数晶格向量G和
prime you must have K minus K prime
equal a reciprocal lattice vector G and
我们在上一讲中得出的等效条件是布拉格条件
we derived in the last lecture that's
equivalent to be Bragg condition to be
正弦theta等于和lambda换句话说，因为倒易晶格
sine theta equals and lambda in other
words since the reciprocal lattice
向量与晶格平面族正交
vector is orthogonal to a family of
lattice planes what you're actually
从具有晶格面间距D的衍射光栅上衍射
getting is diffraction off a diffraction
grating with lattice plane spacing D
正交于该向量G的散射强度
orthogonal to that vector G the
intensity of scattering at any
倒易晶格矢量与结构因子成正比
reciprocal lattice vector is
proportional to the structure factor of
d平方，其中结构因子是散射的傅立叶变换
d squared where the structure factor is
the Fourier transform of the scattering
单位晶格中的电位，因此该强度使您
potential in the unit cell so this
intensity gives you some amount of
有关单位单元中实际存在的信息的信息
information about what's actually in the
unit cell now how you actually do this
实验要复杂一些，可以采用几种方法
experiment is a little more complicated
there's several methods one can go about
有第一种方法是最好的方法，但也是最困难的方法
there is the first method which is the
best method but also the hardest method
最佳但最困难的方法，我将仅就最佳方法进行简要讨论，但
best but hardest which I'll discuss only
very briefly for the best method but
最困难的方法是使用单晶硅
also the hardest method is to use a
single crystal single crystal so single
晶体看起来像这样，这是钠的华丽单晶
crystals look like this this is a
gorgeous single crystal of sodium
氯化物一大块没有任何缺陷的材料现在是什么
chloride a big single piece of the
material without any defects now what
你会发现，所以你把你的单晶放在你的路径
you'll find so you take your single
crystal you put it in the path of your
你的波浪，你寻找我们的波浪从它散落的东西，你
of your wave and you look for for our
waves being scattered off of it what you
发现的是，如果您付钱拿单晶，您可以任意放
find is if you pay take your single
crystal you put it in some arbitrary
在您的光束前方定向，以获得最大定向
orientation in front of your your beam
here for a most orientation
您根本不会有任何分散，换句话说，您将无法对齐
you won't get any scattering at all in
other words you will not manage to align
正好成直角的晶格族
the families of lattice planes just at
the right angle such that the Bragg
条件是实际满足的，所以为了得到任何散射
condition is actually satisfied so in
order to actually get any scattering
您需要做的是旋转晶体旋转晶体
what you need to do is to rotate the
crystal rotate the crystal another way
得到散射是改变波长，非常λ做一个或
to get scattering is to vary the
wavelengths very lambda do one or the
其他，然后在晶体的某个角度或在波的某个值
other and then at some angle of the
crystal or at some value of the wave
得到散射的长度，然后写下获得散射的方向
length you get scattering you write down
in which direction to get the scattering
您可以测量散射的强度，并可以推断出很多
you measure the intensity of the
scattering and you can deduce a lot of
有关结构因素的信息，因此有关
information about the structure factor
and therefore about the structure of the
现在，我们实际上不会讨论如何在任何情况下分析此类数据
crystal now we're not actually going to
go into how you analyze such data in any
本课程中的细节，而我们不打算这样做的原因是因为
detail in this course and the reason
we're not going to do it is because this
方法很少使用，之所以很少使用是因为
method is very rarely used and the
reason it's very rarely used is because
这实际上是最难的事情，因为这很难，因为
it's actually the hardest thing to do
the reason it's hard is because almost
无一例外的材料不喜欢形成漂亮的大晶体钠
without exception materials don't like
to form nice big crystals sodium
氯化物是一个建议，你有这些美丽的钠大晶体
chloride is a suggest and you have these
beautiful big crystals of sodium
氯化石英可以制成漂亮的大晶体，您知道您可能可以制成漂亮的晶体
chloride quartz makes nice big crystals
you know you can probably make a nice
大块的糖晶体，我的意思是，所以有几种材料
big crystal of sugar something I mean so
there are a couple of materials that you
可以形成漂亮的大晶体，但是如果您煮一些，大多数材料就不会
can get to form a nice big crystals but
most materials don't if you cook up some
您实验室中的新材料，或者您通常会在自然界中发现一些新材料
new material in your laboratory or you
find some new material in nature usually
它不是结晶它不会经常形成大晶体它是粉末甚至是
it's not crystalline it doesn't form big
crystals frequently it's powder or even
更糟糕的是，您可以拥有所谓的多晶，所以这是
worse than that you can have what's
known as polycrystalline so this is a
多晶材料的图片，其中有微小的小晶体
picture of a polycrystalline material
where you have tiny little crystal
大约一微米大小的灯，所以这里有一个小水晶
lights which are about on the size of a
micron so there's a little crystal here
一点水晶般清晰，那些水晶的轴方向错误
a little crystal clear and those
crystals have their axes Mis oriented
彼此之间，它们都被弄脏了
with respect to each other and they're
all sort of smushed together you can
认为它就像是粘在一起的微小小晶体粉末，
think of it as like a powder of tiny
little crystals all stuck together and
通常，当您制作材料时，其外观如下所示：
typically materials look like this when
you make them it's very very difficult
需要非常好的化学家和非常好的材料科学家
it takes a very good chemist and very
good material scientist to turn
看起来像这样的东西看起来像这样的东西
something that looks like this into
something that looks like this so most
在做一个实验的时候人们正在做某事
of the time when one is doing the
experiment one is working with something
看起来像是多晶的，所以两个
that looks like this it's
polycrystalline so two
要使用多晶样品获取数据，您可以使用所谓的德拜
to take data on a polycrystalline sample
you use what's known as the Debye
Scherer提出的Scherer方法
Scherer method due by Scherer
作者是来自Debye振动和固体理论的人Scherer
the by is the same guy from the Debye
theory of vibrations and solids Scherer
显然是别人，德拜警长法也叫火药
someone else obviously and the Debye
sheriff method is also known as powder
衍射衍射，因为您可以使用多种材料的粉末
diffraction diffraction because you can
use a powder of the material lots of
微小的小小的水晶灯在粉末中，你可以把它放在你的
tiny tiny little crystal lights in a
powder and you can put that in your
采样并从中获取数据，现在就真正理解它了
sample and get data out of it and
actually make sense of it now the
粉末衍射或在其上进行衍射的思想的一般原理
general principle of the idea of powder
diffraction or doing diffraction on
多晶样品是如果您要向您的产品中发送电波
polycrystalline samples is if you're
sending a wave into your into your
水晶在这里，如果你想像了一秒钟，你会得到一个大生物，一个大单身
crystal here if you imagine for a second
you got a big critter a big single
晶体，如果有任何晶体，您可以旋转该晶体
crystal and you could rotate that single
crystal around if there was any
他旋转单晶的方向，你会得到
direction in which he rotated that
single crystal and you could get
以该角度衍射出来，然后在粉末中的某处
diffraction out at this angle then
somewhere in your powder somewhere in
您的多晶样品的轴将在其他方向正确定向
your polycrystalline sample the axes
will be correctly oriented in other
多晶材料或粉末代表一切可能
words the poly crystal material or the
powder represents every possible
材料的方向，因此在材料的某个地方会有情况
orientation of the material so somewhere
in your material you'll have a situation
您的晶格平面族以正确的方式按顺序对齐
where your family of lattice planes is
aligned just in the right way in order
如果有任何方向可以做到从K到K Prime的衍射
to get diffraction from K to K Prime if
there's any orientation that will do it
您会在您的某处找到正确方向的水晶灯
you'll find that crystal light with the
right orientation somewhere in your
样本好吧，这是我们要遵循的一般原则
sample okay
that's the general principle we're gonna
如果你能在这个方向上得到一些衍射
live by now if if you can get
diffraction in this direction with some
通过这种方式平行排列的晶格平面，您还可以想象
lattice planes that are sort of lined up
parallel this way you can also imagine
如果您以这种方式排列晶格平面，则可能会衍射出来
that if you lined up your lattice planes
this way you could get diffraction out
这样，实际上您可以想象绕着旋转水晶灯
this way and in fact you can imagine
rotating those crystal lights around the
入射轴，您意识到可以获得整个衍射锥
incoming axis and you realize that you
can get a whole cone of diffraction
如果有可以分散的方向，可以向外旋转
outwards if there's any direction that
you can scatter you can rotate that
进入通道周围的水晶灯，并得到圆锥形的出射波
crystal light around the incoming access
and get a get a cone of outgoing waves
因此，实验实际在设置中的外观就像这样
so the way the experiment actually looks
in a set up is kind of like this there's
入射的X射线有多晶和粉末
an incident x-ray
there's a poly crystal and a powder
粉末状的标本在这里，然后您得到这些圆锥形的出射波，
powdered specimen here and then you get
these cones of outgoing waves which you
然后尝试衡量一下​​，请记住在此处标记了该标记，这样您就不会忘记
then try to measure remember that the
it's marked here so you don't forget the
总偏转角为2θ非常重要
total deflection angle is 2 theta very
important a common source of source of
错误和2 theta可以从零到任何地方，这意味着它根本不会分散
error and 2 theta can go anywhere from
zero meaning it's not scattered at all
到180度，这意味着它已经像以前那样直接反向散射
to 180 degrees meaning it's directly
backscattered now the way one used to
测量它是您将采用这种圆形环境，并且您将
measure it is you would take this sort
of round environment and you would line
里面装有相纸，您只需将相纸曝光
the inside with photographic paper and
you just expose the photographic paper
看到X射线，您会看到这些圆锥形信号发出
to the x-rays and you can see these nice
conical signals coming out for these
从您的多晶样品中得出各种不同的锥体
various different cones coming out like
this from your polycrystalline sample
但在现代，不使用相纸的数量更多
but in modern days photographic paper is
not used it's much more it's much more
方便，实际上更准确，使用起来更灵敏
convenient and actually much more
accurate and much more sensitive to use
半导体探测器，因此通常是您实际从样品中得到的
semiconductor detectors so it's usually
what you actually get out of your sample
现在您的实验中出现的是这样的情节，
out of your experiment now is a plot
that looks like this where what's
绘制在底部的是散射角和强度
plotted across the bottom is a
scattering angle and the intensity
垂直，所以您会看到这里有一个二十度左右的峰
vertically so you'll see there's a peak
here at twenty-something degrees another
在30度左右达到峰值，可能与此环相对应，然后
peak at 30 something degrees which might
correspond to this ring and then that
响等等，这就是我们要花费他们的数据类型
ring and so forth and this is the kind
of data that we're going to spend their
时间分析还可以，所以这些都是经典问题的一种
time analyzing okay so these are sort of
sort of a classic type of question for
检查使用设备Scherer方法分析粉末衍射图
exams analyze a powder diffraction
pattern with the device Scherer method
因此，遵循此方法有一些规则，因此我将其写下来
so there's a couple rules for following
this method so I'll write them down it's
很难找到一本能很好地解释这本书的书
fairly difficult to find a book that
explains this well I think is explained
我的书很好，但是如果您不喜欢我的书中的解释，那您就很好
well in my book but if you don't like
the explanation in my book you're kind
之所以运气不好，是因为没有很多其他书籍对此有所解释
of out of luck because there aren't a
lot of other books that explain it so
对此感到抱歉，但事实就是如此
sorry about that but that's just how it
is
所以规则编号零是没有波长没有波长λ为什么你
so rule number zero is no the wavelength
no your wavelength lambda why do you
很好地了解您的波长λ，您就是放入X射线的实验者
know your wavelength lambda well you're
the experimentalist you put in the x-ray
您拥有X射线设备的光束，因此您大概知道
beam you had the x-ray apparatus so you
know presumably what the wavelength of
X射线很重要，所以最好从没有波长开始
the x-ray is so it's a good thing to
start with no your wavelength probably
如果您是优秀的实验师，那么实际上可以很准确地知道它
know it pretty accurately actually if
you're a good experimentalist step one
测量角度测量角度散射角
measure the angles
measure angles angle of scattering which
是两个theta都没有theta记住这很重要，所以这里有一些
is two theta naught theta remember that
it's gonna be important so here's some
数据，我们实际上将要分析他们完成前两个步骤的位置
data we're actually going to analyze
where they've done the first two steps
因为这是铝，他们在散布铝
for this is aluminum they're doing
scattering off of or aluminium I guess
在这个国家，波长在这方面是非常精确的
in this country and the the wavelength
is known extremely precisely in this
设置是通过典型的X射线管完成的，您知道自己有六位数
setup this is done with a typical x-ray
tube and you know you have six digits of
他们知道波长的精确度要记住
precision as to how much how precisely
they know the wavelength remember the
他们如此精确地知道其波长的原因是因为这是
reason they know their wavelength so
precisely is because this is an
原子中两个本征态之间的电子跃迁是电子
electronic transition between two
eigenstates in an atom it's an electron
从一个本征态下降到另一个本征态，所以能量是
falling down from one eigen state to
another eigen state so the energies are
这些本征态非常精确地定义，所以您知道
those eigen states are very very
precisely defined so you so you know the
波长非常高的精度，那么您就会知道所有这些数据
wavelength with very high precision then
you you know you get this data all these
峰值是散射角2θ的函数，幸运的是
Peaks as a function of scattering angle
2 theta and fortunately in this
一张特定的图片他们实际上为我们测量了38个角度
particular picture they've actually
measured the angles for us thirty-eight
点四三度四十四点六七度，依此类推，
point four three degrees forty four
point six seven degrees and so forth and
我还用字母标记了峰，以便我们跟踪它们。
I've also labeled the peaks with letters
so we can keep track of them peak a peak
C峰等等，只是一个提示，如果您曾经服用过粉末
peak C and so forth just a one hint that
if you're ever given a powder
衍射图样，您必须自己测量角度
diffraction pattern and you have to
measure the angles yourself it will
如果您获得非常精确的角度，对您有很大帮助
really help a lot if you get the angles
very precise if you get the angles off
一点点，你会很困惑，这不会很明显
by a little bit you can get very
confused it won't be obvious what the
结果应该是这样，请尝试尽可能精确地对其进行测量
result is supposed to be so try to
measure it as precisely as you can okay
所以对于每个散射角，您要测量步长两个角
so for each scattering angle you measure
step two angle sorry
角度，所以第二步是计算晶格平面间距
angle so step two is calculate the
lattice plane spacing so lattice plane
使用布拉格定律确定平面间距，即d等于2上的lambda
spacing plane spacing using Bragg's law
and that is d equals lambda over two
正弦θ好，所以对于每个散射角
sine theta
okay so for each scattering angle you
看到它代表间距D等于的一族晶格平面
see that's representing a family of
lattice planes with the spacing D equals
Lambda超过两个正弦θ，现在您可能会认为它应该是n
lambda over two sine theta
now you might think it should be n
Lambda超过两个正弦波theta，但实际上您不需要在这里结束，因为
lambda over two sine theta but in fact
you don't need the end up here because
n的较高值将对应于不同的Thetas
the higher values of n will correspond
to different Thetas that you will also
测量一下，所以如果放在楼上，那你就结束了
measure so you'll just be over
if you put in an upstairs so you just
需要将λ保持在2个正弦θ以上，每个角度对应一个
need to keep lambda over 2 sine theta
each angle corresponds to one one
晶格平面间距好吧，所以第三步，对我们来说这是
lattice plane spacing okay all right so
step three so this is for us this is
不在现实世界中，我们可以假设某种立方
sort of not in the real world we can
assume cubic of some sort assume cubic
在现实世界中，对简单立方的含义实际上不是一个坏假设
it's actually not a bad assumption in
the real world to meaning simple cubic
我在25年的考试中从未见过的简单BCC或FCC
simple BCC or FCC I have never seen in
25 years of exams I have never seen a
要求您找出粉末衍射图的三年级考试
third-year exam that is asked you to
figure out a powder diffraction pattern
对于比简单立方BCC或FCC更复杂的事情，
for anything more complicated than
simple cubic BCC or FCC those are the
您在三年级考试中只会碰到的格子几乎是一个承诺
only lattices you'll run into on your
third year exam that's almost a promise
我的意思是您当然知道他们第一次可以做些什么，但是
I mean of course you know they could do
something for the first time but but
你很漂亮，这是一个很好的假设，那就是你永远不会
you're pretty it's pretty good
assumption that this is all you're never
会在现实世界中碰到的是，你会碰到更多的东西
gonna run into in the real world it's
you'll run into things that are more
复杂，但以此为前提开始，如果
complicated but it's not a bad thing to
start with this as an assumption and if
您无法获取适合这些数据的数据，然后继续进行更复杂的操作
you can't get the data to fit these then
you go on to more complicated
假设立方的可能性还可以，我们也将记住
possibilities all right assuming cubic
we also have will remember that the
晶格平面间距这是我们根据米勒得出的
lattice plane spacing this is something
we derived corresponding to Miller
指数HKL是晶格常数a除以H平方的平方根
indices HKL is the lattice constant a
divided by the square root of H squared
加K平方加l平方这是我们最后得出的结果
plus K squared plus l squared it's
something we derived I think in the last
讲座也许是之前的那一场，那么这给我们带来了什么呢？
lecture maybe the one before so what
does that give us that gives us that a
d平方的平方是H平方加K平方加l平方现在我们不
squared over d squared is H squared plus
K squared plus l squared now we don't
知道是什么，我们将尝试找出答案，但我们知道许多DS
know what a is yet we're gonna try to
figure it out but we know a bunch of DS
那么这是要告诉我们DS的比例将是这些HKS和elzar
so is this gonna tell us the ratio of DS
are going to be these HKS and elzar
整数，所以1与d平方的比将是一个整数
integers so the ratio of 1 over d
squared are going to be an integer
比率确定，所以我们要声明这个东西H的平方加K
ratios ok so we're going to declare this
thing this quantity H squared plus K
平方乘以l平方，我们将其称为N，然后让我们看看我们还有什么
squared over l squared we're gonna call
it N and step let's see what else we're
到第四步为止，我们将寻找整数的整数比率
stuff to up to step four we're going to
look for integer ratios for integer
比率
ratios
n的比率，然后获得n的整数比率后，我们将寻找
ratios of n and then once we have the
integer ratios of n we will look for
选择规则寻找选择规则
selection rules look for selection rules
规则，规则，好的，让我们从最后回想一下
rules rules okay
so let's let's recall from the last
讲座如果我们有一个简单的三次方，将给HKL选择规则
lecture what the selection rules were
given HKL if we had a simple cubic
格子简单立方格子所有HKL允许所有HKL对应倒数
lattice simple cubic lattice all HKL are
allowed all HKL correspond to reciprocal
简单立方大声晶格的晶格矢量，因此全部允许
lattice vectors for the simple cubic
loud lattice so these are all allowed
对于BCC晶格，我们推导了选择规则：h加k加LL
for a BCC lattice we derived the
selection rule that h plus k plus L L
对于FCC晶格，必须为偶数，必须为偶数。
must be even must be even for an FCC
lattice we derived the selection rule
然后h KL全部为偶数或全为奇数，这样我们就可以开始制作一个
then h KL all even or all odd so we can
actually start making a table of the
实际上，可能我会把桌子放在这里
possibilities actually maybe I'll put
the table over here
所以在第一列上会把HKL放到最后一个家庭
so over first column will put HKL this
is the family possible families last
位置将写出n为H平方加K平方加l平方的数字n
place will write the number n which is H
squared plus K squared plus l squared
然后我们将编写简单的立方BCC和FCC并询问是否允许使用
and then we'll write simple cubic BCC
and FCC and ask whether they're allowed
那么我们所说的最简单的最后一架飞机是什么
so what's the simplest possible family
of last planes we could be talking about
我们可能在说1 0 0，所以n H平方加K平方加l平方是
we could be talking about 1 0 0 so n H
squared plus K squared plus l squared is
1个简单立方是允许所有简单立方
1 simple cubic
yes that's allowed for simple cubic all
H平方加K允许​​所有HK和L用于简单立方BCC，这不是
H squared plus K all H K and L are
allowed for simple cubic BCC it's not
允许，因为1加0加0为奇数，所以这是不允许的FCC，因为
allowed because 1 plus 0 plus 0 is odd
so this is no FCC is not allowed because
它们不是全部都是奇数，甚至不是全部，所以FCC不允许下一个
they're not all odd or all even so it's
not allowed for FCC how about the next
最简单1 1 1 0 H平方加K平方加l平方为2简单立方
simplest 1 1 1 0 H squared plus K
squared plus l squared is 2 simple cubic
是的，这也允许BCC 1加1加0等于1加1加0是
well yes that's also allowed BCC well 1
plus 1 plus 0 is even 1 plus 1 plus 0 is
2，所以允许，是FCC，这是不允许的，因为他们都不都是奇怪的人
2 so that's allowed yes FCC it's not
allowed because they're not all odd who
甚至一个一一对一的HBO Chris K Fidel平方是三
are all even one one one one
HBO Chris K Fidel squared is three it's
允许用于BCC的简单三次，这是不允许的，因为总和是奇数，但
allowed for simple cubic for BCC it's
not allowed because the sum is odd but
FCC允许使用，因为它们都是奇数，然后2 0 0继续前进
it is allowed for FCC because they're
all odd then 2 0 0 keep going
所以2平方加0平方是4它允许简单立方的和是偶数
so 2 squared plus 0 squared is 4 it's
allowed for simple cubic the sum is even
所以这里允许，他们都可以，所以你可以
so it's allowed here and they're all
even so it's allowed here and you can
组成这些事情的一个大表值得跟踪
make up a big table of these things it's
worth doing to keep track of which
您应该从中观察Miller索引现在从哪种可能的晶格类型开始
Miller indices you should observe for
which possible lattice type now from
这种类型的表格可以列出可能的整数，并且您可以
this type of table you can make a list
of the possible integers and that you
会看到不同的晶格类型，因此对于简单立方立方
would see for the different lattice
types for so for simple cubic cubic you
得到，得到的可能结局是1 2 3 4 5 6 8所以7发生了什么
get and the possible ends you get are 1
2 3 4 5 6 8 so what happened to 7 so all
允许使用可能的HKS和ELL，但是您会发现是否尝试了
the possible HKS and ELLs are allowed
but you'll discover if you try there's
如果您将它们平方并拿走H就没有了
no H can
all that if you square them and take H
平方加K平方加l平方，您将得到7，但找不到它
squared plus K squared plus l squared
you'll get 7 you just can't find it sort
数论类型的结果，您只是找不到三个整数
of a number theory type of result that
you just can't find three integers that
当平方和加在一起就给你七个，所以七个不见了，依此类推
when squared and added together give you
seven so seven is missing and so forth
我认为下一个缺少的是BCC的15个BCC和2 4 6 8个
and I think the next one that's missing
is 15 for BCC for BCC and is 2 4 6 8 so
依此类推，我想缺少的第一个是28，实际上FCC是
最有趣的一个FCC系列是N等于3 3 4 8 11 12 16 16等等
most interesting one FCC the series is N
equals 3 3 4 8 11 12 16 16 and so forth
其实我想我已经把这些写下来了，是的，这不是
actually I think I wrote these all down
already yeah it's not on this on this
幻灯片，因此我们再次将整个表格写下来，
slide so here's exactly building that
whole table again we wrote down the
该表的前四个元素这是端点正方形加K正方形加l
first four elements of this table here's
the ends a square plus K square plus l
平方1 2 3 4 5 6到7时，没有米勒指数集
squared 1 2 3 4 5 6 when you get to 7
there's no set of Miller indices that
平方并加在一起得到7，然后您查看FCC以及
went squared and add together gives you
7 and you look at FCC and the possible
可能为您提供的FCC允许的Miller指数
the possible Miller indices that give
you that are allowed for FCC the first
第一个是1 1 1这些都是奇数，总共3个
the first one is 1 1 1 those are all odd
that that gives you a total of 3 the
允许的下一个是2 0 0这些全都等于2的平方
next one that's allowed is 2 0 0 those
are all even that gives you 2 squared
加0加0平方是4表示允许，下一个允许的是2
plus 0 plus 0 squared is 4 that's
allowed the next one that's allowed is 2
2 0全部偶数2平方加2平方加0平方等于8下一个是
2 0 all even 2 squared plus 2 squared
plus 0 squared is 8 the next one that's
允许的是3 1 1所有的奇数使您得到11，依此类推，所以这是系列
allowed is 3 1 1 all odd that gives you
11 and so forth so these are the series
我们想要寻找的，所以实际上让我们为这种铝做
that we want to want to look for so
actually let's do that for this aluminum
数据哦，他们在这里，所以这是写出来的系列1 2 3 4 5 6 8 9
data oh and they here so here's the
series written out 1 2 3 4 5 6 8 9
缺少七十五和二十三我都连整数都不包括28 60和
missing seven fifteen and twenty three I
all even integer is excluding 28 60 and
依此类推，这并非巧合28恰好是7和60的4倍
so forth actually it's not a coincidence
of 28 happens to be 4 times 7 and 60
碰巧是15的4倍，您可以说服自己为什么如此
happens to be 4 times 15 you can
convince yourself why that's true and
那么FCC是3 4 8 11 12，以此类推，所以这又是数据
then FCC is 3 4 8 11 12 and and and so
forth okay so here's the data again
让我们一步一步地完成此过程，所以在这里我们测量了所有
let's go through this procedure all the
steps one by one so here we measured all
的角度或有人测量了四个
of the the angles or someone measured
four
这是他们很好的一面，所以让我们计算出所有这些角度的表D
here is very nice of them here so make a
table of all these angles we calculate D
等于2正弦theta上的lambda，所以这里是所有2正弦theta上的lambda
equals lambda over 2 sine theta so here
is the lambda over 2 sine theta for all
这些散射峰中的一个，那么我们得出以下结论：d平方上有108
of these scattering Peaks then we have
this statement that 108 over d squared
在d平方上是H平方加K平方加l平方，我们想
over d squared is H squared plus K
squared plus l squared and we want to
求出1的平方的整数比率，所以我们要怎么做呢？
find integer ratios of 1 over d squared
so how do we do that well let's declare
这个数字在这里是2点3 4哦5埃，我们称之为D sub a
this number here two point three four oh
five angstroms we'll call that D sub a
然后我们将D sub的表平方成d平方，其中D是全部
and we'll make a table of D sub a
squared over d squared where D is is all
这些D的可能值中的一个，因此第一个时隙在定义上为12.3平方
of these possible values of D so the
first slot is by definition 12.3 squared
在两点三平方上是一，但在第二个一两点三平方上
over two point three squared is one but
the second one two point three squared
在2点O 2平方上是1点3 3等等，依此类推
over two point O two squared is one
point three three and so forth and so on
我们在这张表中得到这些不是整数，但它们非常接近
we get this in this table here those
aren't integers but they're pretty close
整数，如果乘以三，则会得到一组
to integers if you're multiplying by
three you get a set of things that are
真的非常接近整数，您会发现该模式实际上是3
really really close to integers and
you'll see that that pattern is really 3
4 8 11 12 16 1920这是FCC系列3 4 8 11 12 16 19 20
4 8 11 12 16 1920 which is the FCC
series 3 4 8 11 12 16 19 20 so so we've
由此得出的结论是，我们发现铝的铝散射模式
concluded from this that the aluminum
the aluminum scattering pattern we found
对应于FCC晶格，我们实际上可以进一步
is corresponds to an FCC lattice we can
actually go on a little bit further to
计算晶格常数，所以这可能是步骤5
calculate lattice constants so this
might be step 5
计算晶格常数，单位晶格常数a的大小为
calculate lattice constant the size of
the unit cell constant a which would be
d乘以K平方的平方根再加上l平方再加上一个平方，因为我
d times the square root of K squared
plus l squared plus a squared because I
以错误的顺序做了一个正方形加K平方加L平方通常没事
did in the wrong order a square plus K
square plus l squared usually all right
同样的事情，如果我们这样做，那么哦，这是写下来的米勒指数
same thing and if we do that oh they're
the Miller indices written down for
它们是山峰，这是A，它们都差不多
their for the peaks and here's the A's
and they're all pretty close to the same
大约三到四位数，它们并不完全相同，所以可能
to about three or four digits they're
not exactly the same so there's probably
角度测量中出现了一些错误或类似的错误
some error in the measurement of the
angles or something like that has gone
错误，但在四位数的精度以内，我们已经测量了晶格
wrong but to within four digits of
accuracy we've measured the lattice
常数a表示铝还可以，所以现在一般来说就是这样
constant a for aluminum okay so that's
generally how it works now when you get
擅长于此，您甚至不必真正进行整个计算
good at this you don't even
have to really do this whole calculation
您可以看一下模式我非常清楚这是什么
you can sort of look at the pattern I
have a pretty good idea what it is so
哦，有铝，有
this
oh there's aluminum there there's the
Miller索引标记正确，所以我将向您展示一种模式，
the Miller indices labeled appropriately
so I'm going to show you a pattern and
无需进行任何计算，我们就能知道现在的晶格类型
without actually doing any calculation
we can tell what the lattice type is now
如果您给我一个理由，只是给我一个理由，只有三种可能性
there's only three possibilities if you
give me a reason just give me a reason a
简单三次，这是什么原因，很好的原因是什么，所以没有7是
simple cubic what's the reason very good
alright so that's a so no seven that's a
那是你的，所以你可以在这里看到第一个高峰，这样
that one's yours so you can see here
that the first peak so that the the
峰间距不完全均匀，这是因为正弦
spacing of the peaks is not completely
uniform and that's because of the sine
正弦theta的theta因子可让您在离开时获得更多空间
theta factor that sine theta sort of
spaces things out more when you're at
小角度比大角度，但您可以看到
low angles than it is it's at high
angles but but you can kind of see that
一从一到二的间距不是这样
one
the spacing from one to two isn't so
从2到3 3到4 4到5 5到6不同，但是有一个洞，其中7是
different from 2 to 3 3 to 4 4 to 5 5 to
6 but then there's a hole where 7 is
应该是然后8到9 10 11 12，你看他们是否真的有一个
supposed to be and then 8 to 9 10 11 12
and you see if they actually there's a
孔应该在15的位置，如果一路上升到23
hole where 15 is supposed to be and if
you go all the way up to 23 you'll
注意，应该是一个洞或23，这就是您期望的系列
notice as a hole or 23 is supposed to be
and that's the series that you expect
对于简单的三次方，您只需在此散射图上查看
for simple cubic so you can just look at
this at this scattering pattern for a
钛酸钡，知道钛酸钡是简单的立方晶格
barium titanate and know that barium
titanate is a simple cubic lattice okay
这样就可以了
that's how it works pretty cool all
right
顺便说一句，钛酸钡是一种非常重要的光电材料
incidentally barium titanate is a fairly
important material for the opto
电子行业，它用于各种各样的事情，现在有更多
electronics industry it's used for
various things now there's more
信息中有更多分散的信息
information in this there is there's
more information in this scattering
到目前为止，我们所使用的模式只是散射角度
pattern than we've used so far all we've
used is the angles of scattering we
没有使用任何有关散射强度的东西，
haven't used anything about the
intensity of scattering and there's a
我们可以利用的大量散射强度信息
lot of information in the intensity of
scattering that we can make use of
所以让我们来看看是否可以理解我们应该得到多少散射
so let's um see if we can understand
what how much scattering we should get
来自Miller指数HKL首先，香港存在结构因子s
from Miller indices HKL well first of
all there's the structure factor s at HK
现在平方的L还可以写出来，所以结构
L which gets squared now all right let's
even write it out so the structure
记住这个s等于s乘以s的基数
factor remember this s equals s lattice
times s basis
乘以s的基础和s的格子，无非是强制选择规则
times s basis and s lattice does nothing
more than enforced selection rules
强制执行选择规则，这样我们就可以做到
enforce selection rules so we've done
that so that's not going to be
对我们的基础很有趣，因为在这个基础上只有一个原子
interesting for us s basis well there's
only one atom in this basis because it's
只是一种类型的原子一个单一的单个原子，因为它只是纯FCC
just one type of atom a single single
atom on the basis it's just a pure FCC
没有培根的格子没有有趣的基础，所以您得到的只是表格
lattice with no bacon no interesting
basis so all you get is the the form
铝的系数，而铝衰变的形状因数
factor for aluminum and this form factor
for aluminum decays decays with
随着我们上次提到的G的增加或增加而增加
increasing with increasing increasing G
as we mentioned last time or increasing
角度或增加的θ增加，所以我们期望总散射为
angle or increased increase theta so we
expect that the total scattering is
会随着散射角的增加而缓慢下降，但是有
going to drop slowly as a function of
increased scattering angle but there's
实际上，这并不是所有导致强度增加的因素，还有另外两个
actually that's not all that contributes
to the the intensity there's two other
首先影响强度的因素是概率
factors which contribute to the
intensity at first is the probability
对齐的可能性，所以这是微晶将
probability of alignment so this is the
probability that a crystallite will
以正确的方式对齐以获取散射，我们将回到
align in just the right way in order to
get scattering we'll come back to that
一会儿，最后一个因素被称为洛伦兹因子洛伦兹或
in a moment and the last factor is known
as the Lorentz factor Lorentz or
有时洛伦兹极化因子是
sometimes the Lorentz polarization
factor the polarization factor which is
确实是一个几何因素，我们对此不多说，但我会
really a geometric factor we're not
going to say too much about it but I'll
向您展示它的外观，因此该函数是X随其变化的函数
show you what it looks like so this
function is a function which X it varies
作为角度的函数相当快，但随后在中间的任何地方
fairly rapidly as a function of angle
but then anywhere near at intermediate
角度大约在60到140之间比较平坦，然后又回升
angles it's fairly flat between around
60 and 140 and then it goes back up
最终在140左右开始回升，这是洛伦兹极化
eventually at around 140 it starts going
back up it's the Lorentz polarization
因素，这实际上是您如何设置实验的功能，因此，如果您
factor it's really a feature of how you
set up your experiment and so if you're
实验师，您会提前知道这个因素是什么
an experimentalist you will know what
this factor is in advance before you do
进行任何测量之前，现在有一个
any sort of before you do any sort of
measurement now there's a there's our
而不是这里有时是什么时候
instead of a
which here which is that sometimes when
人们会像这样向您展示X射线图
people present you with x-ray patterns
like this one
他们已经在这里除以洛伦兹极化系数，
they'll have already divided by the
Lorentz polarization factor here and
其他时候他们将不会除以洛伦兹极化系数，因此
other times they will not have divided
by the Lorentz polarization factor so
真的，如果有人向您显示这样的数据，您应该问的是原始数据或
really if someone shows you data like
this you should ask is that raw data or
你已经用这个洛伦兹极化因子除了吗？
have you divided out by this Lorentz
polarization factor already and
在许多考试中足够令人尴尬的是，他们会问你一个问题，他们
embarrassingly enough on many exams
they'll ask you a question and they
不会告诉你他们是否被这个除法了
won't tell you whether they've divided
by this or not
因此，如果您想安全起见，应该说您应该告诉我您是否
so if you want to be safe you should say
you should have told me whether you're
除以这个因素，我无论如何都假设是这样
divided by this factor or not I'm
assuming whatever so anyway so that's
这就是这个因素，对于大多数角度也是如此，所以在这里我们只是分散
that's this factor and it also for most
angles so here we're only scattering up
到这里大约120度，所以这个因素在这里衰减为
to about 120 degrees here so this so
this factor here is decaying as a
高达120度的角度的函数，此因子在这里也随着
function of angle up to 120 degrees this
factor here is also decaying as a
角度的函数，所以我们天真地猜测我们应该始终
function of angle so we'd sort of
naively guess that we should always
随着角度的增加和/或多或少地衰减作为角度的函数
decay as a function of angle as you
increase the angle and and more or less
散射幅度随着角度的变化而衰减，但是我们还没有
the scattering amplitude is decaying as
a function of angle but we haven't
在这里看了这块，我们对齐的可能性很好
looked at this piece here our
probability of alignment well you might
想想自己，您知道所有的微晶都是完全对齐的
think to yourself you know all the
crystallites are aligned completely
随机，因此该因子应该是微不足道的，它应该只是1，但是认为
randomly so that that factor should be
trivial it should be just be 1 but think
一秒钟的时间，您会记得当我们谈论晶格族时
about this for a second you'll remember
when we talked about families of lattice
平面，如果我们正在考虑与
planes if we're thinking about a lattice
plane spacing which is associated with
1：1一族的晶格平面本来可以是一对一的家族
the 1:1 one family of lattice planes it
could have been the one one one family
晶格平面或1 1 bar 1或1 bar 1 1或1 bar 1 bar 1 I
of lattice planes or the 1 1 bar 1 or
the 1 bar 1 1 or the 1 bar 1 bar 1 I
意味着有八种可能性都可以让您完全一样
mean there's eight possibilities which
would all give you exactly the same
您可以分散的晶格平面间距
lattice plane spacing that you can
scatter off of so in fact this
对齐的可能性实际上是HKL的倍数，所以如果我们回到
probability of alignment is actually the
multiplicity of HKL so if we go back to
如果您要在此表格中查看您将多重性添加到此表格的位置
this table here to see where ya add the
multiplicities on to this table if we're
考虑1 0 0 M Miller指数有六个可能的方向
thinking about the 1 0 0 M Miller
indices there's six possible directions
这将呈现与1 0 0相同的晶格平面间距，有6
which would present the same lattice
plane spacing as 1 0 0 there's 6
立方体的可能轴，但如果我们看1 1 0，将有12
possible axes of the cube but if we're
looking at the 1 1 0 there would be 12
可以选择十二种不同的面孔方式
different faces Speight
for twelve different face ways you could
面对立方体，您将呈现相同的晶格平面间距，并且有人
face the cube that you would present the
same lattice plane spacing and someone
因为意识到三对一的心理多样性而赢得了巧克力奖
won a chocolate bar for realizing that
three to one has a mental multiplicity
48之所以这些是我们要跟踪的因素
of 48 so these are the factors that we
want to keep track of if we want to
现在了解散射的强度，让我们看一下
understand the intensity of the
scattering now let's look at this let's
看两个实际上彼此接近一个角度的峰
look at two peaks that are actually
fairly close to each other an angle why
我是不是想看看彼此非常接近的两件事
am I do I want to look at two things
that are fairly close to each other an
如果F和L都随着速度的变化而缓慢衰减
angle well if you both F and L are
decaying kind of slowly as a function of
角度，所以如果我们在中间某个角度拍摄角度，就知道在这里
angle so you know here if we're take if
we take angles somewhere in the middle
你知道在100120左右，那么这个东西很平
you know around 100 120 then then this
thing is pretty flat this thing is
衰减缓慢，我们只能担心多重性，所以让我们
decaying only slowly and we can only
worry about the multiplicity so let's
在这里取得这两个峰3 1 1＆2 2 2 3 1 1＆2 2 2那里他们知道
take these two peaks here 3 1 1 & 2 2 2
3 1 1 & 2 2 2 there they you know they
里面有这些F sandeul，但是F和L几乎一样，因为我们
have these F sandeul's in them but F and
L are pretty much the same because we're
大约以相同的角度散射4 3 1 1＆2 2 2
scattering at about the same angle 4 3 1
1 & 2 2 2 just a slight difference in
角度，但是多重性让我们回到这里的多重性3 1 1
the angle but the multiplicities let's
back up to the multiplicities here 3 1 1
在哪里3 1 1在哪里有24在哪里-2在哪里有
has where is it 3 1 1 has a multiplicity
of 24 where to - 2 has a multiplicity of
8，所以我们猜想3 1 1的峰值应该是峰值的3倍
8 so we would guess that the peak for 3
1 1 should be 3 times higher than the
8的峰值，实际上3 1 1的峰值比3的峰值高近3倍
peak for 8 and indeed the peak for 3 1 1
is pretty close to 3 times higher than
2 2 2的峰值就可以了，这就是多重​​性在游戏中获得的方式
the peak for 2 2 2 okay so that's how
the multiplicities get in in the game as
很好，所以这些散射强度实际上可能非常有用
well okay so these intensities of
scattering can actually be very useful
还要分析数据，我将向您展示一些人为的例子
for analyzing data as well I'm going to
show you a sort of artificial example of
可能有用的地方，所以这里有一些非常糟糕的铁数据
where this might be useful so here is
some fairly bad data for taken on iron
不好的原因有两个，第一个原因是因为山峰
that was bad for a couple reasons
the first reason is because the peaks
第二个原因是因为您只看到三个峰值
are pretty broad the second reason is
because you only see three peaks with
三个峰值很难说出您在谈论哪个系列
three peaks it's pretty hard to tell
which series you're talking about here
您无法数到第七个，看看是否缺少第七个，因为
you can't count out to the seventh and
see if the seventh is missing because
您只有三个峰，这将有些困难，但是
you only have three peaks so this is
going to be a little bit difficult but
我们有散射的幅度，实际上可能是
we have the amplitudes of the scattering
and that actually might be might
会有所帮助，所以我们将看看是否可以利用这一点，因此我们将
be helpful so we'll see if we can we can
make use of that so we go through the
测量角度的相同练习计算晶格平面
same exercise of measuring the the
angles calculate the lattice plane
间距取第一晶格平面间距与各种
spacing take the ratio of the first
lattice plane spacing to the various
晶格平面间距da两点零三平方1.4平方是2是
lattice plane spacing da two point zero
three squared over 1.4 squared is two is
到两点O 3平方超过一分之一七平方约3我们
to two point O 3 squared over one point
one seven squared is about three we
意识到那些是一二和三的整数比，所以那些可能是
realize those are in the integer ratios
of one two and three so those could be
两种可能性，要么是简单的三次方，然后是这些
two possibilities either
it's simple cubic and then these
散射峰对应于1 0 0 1 1 0和1 1 1，表示此整数n H
scattering Peaks correspond to 1 0 0 1 1
0 and 1 1 1 meaning this integer n H
平方加K平方加l平方是1 2或3，也可能是n是2 4＆6
squared plus K squared plus l squared is
1 2 or 3 or it could be n is 2 4 & 6
那些仍然是1 2＆3的比例，但是它们对应于米勒
those would still be in the ratio of 1 2
& 3 but they would correspond to Miller
1 1 0 2 0 0＆2 1 1的索引我将加平方并加起来得到
indices of 1 1 0 2 0 0 & 2 1 1 which I'm
going to add squared and add it up give
您2 4＆6，所以我们仅通过查看这些数据就不知道是哪一个
you 2 4 & 6 so we don't know which one
it is just by looking at the this data
所以我们要做好什么，我们可以采取几种方法
so what do we do well there's a couple
of approaches we could take one approach
是我们可以尝试计算晶格常数a，因此，如果我们计算
is that we could try calculating the the
lattice constant a so if we calculate
可以假设简单的三次方计算晶格常数，
the lattice we could assume simple cubic
calculate the lattice constant and we
将得到D乘以平方的平方根再加上K平方再加上l平方
would get D times square root of a
square plus K squared plus l squared
给我们2.0 3埃，我们对BCC做同样的事情，我们得到的是
gives us 2.0 3 angstroms we did the same
thing for BCC we'd get something that's
2的平方根更大，因为我们将所有末端乘以2，所以这
square root of 2 bigger because we're
multiplying all the ends by 2 so this
平方根里面的东西乘以2，所以不是
thing inside the square root is
multiplied by 2 overall so instead of
指向零点三，我们得到两个点八六好，所以我们有一个
getting to point zero three we get two
point eight six okay so we have a
不同的晶格平面和常规晶胞的尺寸不同
different lattice plane a different size
of the of the unit cell and conventional
现在，对于BCC案例的晶胞，为什么对我们有帮助，因为我们不知道什么
unit cell for a BCC case now why does
that help us because we don't know what
晶格常数适用于铁，但确实可以帮助我们，因为我们可以尝试
the lattice constant is for iron but it
does help us because we could try
计算简单立方情况下的原子密度，我们将有一个原子
calculating the atomic density for the
simple cubic case we would have one atom
每两点O 3埃的立方，而对于BCC，则是两个原子两个
per two point O 3 angstroms cubed
whereas for a BCC it's two atoms two
常规晶胞中每两点八六埃立方的原子和
atoms in the conventional unit cell per
two point eight six angstroms cubes and
这些密度彼此之间的平方根为二，所以如果
those densities differ from each other
by a factor of square root of two so if
我们知道铁的原子密度
we knew the atomic density of iron we
could
是的，所以我们会完成的，但是假设我们不会碰巧知道
which one it is so we'd be done but
suppose we don't happen to know the
铁的原子密度，那么我们该怎么办好吧，还有其他事情
atomic density of iron so what do we do
then okay there are other other things
我们可以调用，我们可以看一下散射幅度
we could invoke we could look at the
scattering amplitudes which was what I
一直领先到现在，所以以这个散射角度
was leading up to now remember so at
this at this scattering angle the
洛伦兹系数不断减小，形状因数总是随着
Lorentz factor is decreasing the form
factor is always decreasing as a
增加角度的功能，因此您会天真地希望a应该是
function of increased angle so you would
sort of naively expect that a should be
大于B应该大于C但不是C大于唯一
bigger than B should be bigger than C
but it's not C is bigger the only thing
这可能解释了如果峰值C的多重性更大
that could possibly explain that is if
the multiplicity of the peak C is bigger
而不是B的多重性，所以如果看简单三次
than the multiplicity of B so if you
look at the simple cubic the simple
三次，我们确定第一个峰是1 0 0，第二个峰是1 1 0，第三个峰
cubic we identify the first peak is 1 0
0 the second peak is 1 1 0 and the third
峰值为1 1 1 B的多重性大于C的多重性
peak as 1 1 1 the multiplicity of B is
bigger than the multiplicity of C so
没有理由让C峰大于B峰
there's no reason you would ever get the
C peak to be bigger than B peak
但是对于BCC，C峰到1 1的多重性是24个单词
however for BCC the multiplicity of the
C peak to 1 1 is 24 words a multiplicity
B峰的峰值是2 0 0，所以如果您现在C实际上应该比B大
of the B peak is 2 0 0 so C should
actually be bigger than B now if you
只是看一下多重性，您期望C应该是4的倍数
just look at the multiplicities you
would expect a factor of 4 that C should
比B大4倍，不比B大4倍，只有大约2倍
be 4 times bigger than B and it's not 4
times bigger than B it's only about two
可能比B大两倍大一点，但它不是完整的原因
maybe two and a bit bigger times bigger
than B but the reason it's not a full
大四倍是因为F在下降，形状因数在下降，
four times bigger is because F is
dropping the form factor is dropping and
洛伦兹系数也在同时下降，因此与此竞争
Lorentz factor is dropping also at the
same time so it's competing with this
降低这两个条件的影响，但只要考虑一下
decreasing effect from these other two
terms but any rates just by looking at
我们可以从振幅中得知，这一定是BC C
this data we can we can tell just from
the amplitudes that this must be BC C of
当然我们也知道铁不是简单的立方，因为只有一个
course we also know that iron is not
simple cubic because there's only one
具有简单立方晶格的元素，即po和铁
element that takes a simple cubic
lattice and that's polonium and iron
不是po，所以它也是一种欺骗的方式
isn't polonium and so that does it also
it's sort of a cheating way to go about
好的，让我们再做一个例子这是中子的例子
it all right so let's do one more
example this is the example of neutron
散射中子散射与X射线散射非常相似，但它是
scattering neutron scattering is very
similar to x-ray scattering but it's a
稍微简单一点，因为形状因子只是一个常数，只是核子
little simpler because the form factor
is just a constant it's just the nuclear
散射长度不是G的函数，所以我的天哪是格子类型
scattering length it's not a function of
G so what's the lattice type oh my gosh
哦，是的，我在这个问题上不太好，所以是的，所以你可以说这是FC
oh yes yes I'm not so good at this um so
yes so it's so you can tell it's it's FC
这是FCC，由于模式不做任何计算
this is FCC without doing any
calculation because of the pattern the
您可以想象一下，如果这是3这是4那么有一个很大的
you can sort of imagine that's if this
is 3 this is 4 then there's a big
到8的间距然后到11的一点间距12靠近在一起，所以您可以看到
spacing to 8 then a little spacing to 11
12 close together so you can kind of see
间距是FCC晶格的正确间距，所以如果您
that the spacing is the right spacing
for an FCC lattice okay so but if you
想要贯穿整个故事我们可以经历整个故事
want to go through the whole the whole
the whole story we can go through the
整个故事仔细测量角度，计算晶格平面间距
whole story carefully measure the angles
calculate the lattice plane spacings
在晶格平面间距的平方上取1对1的比率
take the ratios of a 1 over the 1 over
the square of the lattice plane spacings
你得到一个1.3 2.6我们意识到将这些乘以3我们意识到这些
you get one 1.3 2.6 we realize
multiplies these by 3 we realize these
是整数比率3 4非常接近8非常接近11实际数据
are integer ratios 3 4 pretty close to 8
pretty close to 11 actually the data
并不是很好，如果备份得好，您会意识到这些峰是
isn't so great and if you back up
well you'll realize that these Peaks are
相当广泛，他们不是很准确地知道解决方案不是
pretty broad they're not really that
accurately you know resolved it's not
最好的数据是1959年采集的数据
the greatest data this was data taken in
1959 I mean modern modern data is much
更好，但是好吧，您可以肯定地看到它将会
better but but ok it's you can
definitely see that it's it's going to
成为FCC，您还可以标记米勒指数并获得
be FCC and you can also label the Miller
indices and get an estimate of the
晶格常数好吧，所以晶格常数，也许你不知道
lattice constant okay so the lattice
constant and maybe you don't know it
在百分之几之内，但是您对它的估计是相当不错的，但是
within a few percent but you have a
pretty good estimate of what it is but
事实上，我们在这里拥有的东西，我们可以写出我们可以
in fact what we have here and we can
write out the multiplicities we can
标记峰以及通过执行此操作实际上会注意到您会注意到
label the peaks as well actually notice
that you by doing this you'll notice
您可能已经预测到会有一个轻微的峰，这里的峰为4至0峰
that there's you would have predicted a
slight peak here a peak a 4 to 0 peak
这里没有肩膀
here where the shoulder is it's not
there
我的意思是您，但是如果您仔细地看一下，您会发现其中有些
I mean you but if you kind of look at it
carefully you see that there's kind of a
肩膀虚弱，您可以想象这只是一个很小的峰
weak shoulder you can sort of imagine
that it's just a very small peak that's
现在坐在那里，这样可以告诉我们高峰在哪里，但是我们
sitting there now so this tells us
whether where the peaks are but we
我们想获得更多信息，我们想知道什么
there's more information that we would
like to get we would like to know what
基础是，所以我们知道碳化钛碳化钛是FCC，它
the basis is so we know that titanium
carbide titanium carbide is FCC and it
必须有一个基础，我们有两个基础，两个基础
has to have a basis we the basis it has
two elements in it with the basis of two
两个原子的原子，我们想知道什么是形式
atoms of two atoms
and we'd like to know what is the form
换句话说，您将钛放在哪里
of the basis in other words where do you
put the titanium where you put the
晶胞中的碳，所以我们可以算出好吧，所以我们可以任意
carbon in the unit cell so can we figure
that out well okay so arbitrarily we can
我们总是可以将钛分配到零零零零的位置
we can always assign titanium to the
position at position zero zero zero in
单位晶格我们将钛位置定义为零零零
the unit cell we'll just define the
titanium position to be zero zero zero
但是然后碳将置于uvw位置，我们偶然不知道
but then carbon will put at position uvw
which we don't know incidentally I
应该提到碳化钛实际上是一种非常重要的材料
should have mentioned titanium carbide
is actually a really important material
有谁知道这是另一个有谁知道为什么碳化钛是
does anyone know here's another one
anyone know why titanium carbide is
真的很重要，将它用于需要的任何事情
really important use it for what yeah
yeah anything that needs to be really
很难，那么是的，所以今天任何碳化物都是最难的一种
hard yeah then yeah okay so and so today
any carbide is one of the hardest
那里没有钻石的材料，我认为只有一两个
materials out there short of diamond I
think there's only one or two others
和碳化钛一样坚硬，很容易看到
that are as hard as titanium carbide
it's easy to see it's easier to make
碳化钛，它不比钻石贵，所以无论何时需要
titanium carbide it's not as expensive a
diamond it's so whenever you need
任何需要非常艰苦的事情，它经常用于事物
anything that needs to be very tough
it's very frequently used for things
如工具，如果您需要锯或钻头将要切穿的东西
like tools if you need a saw or a drill
bit that's gonna cut through something
很难，经常是碳化钛，所以这就是为什么
very hard it's very frequently titanium
carbide so that's why they did this
可以追溯到1959年，因为它是一种有趣的材料
experiment way back in in 1959 because
it was an interesting material even back
在1959年，他们甚至都不知道它的结构，所以我认为视频也许
in 1959 and they didn't even know its
structure so okay so I think video maybe
他们不知道其他东西的结构，我不确定，但是
they didn't know the structure from
something else I don't I'm not sure but
我认为他们不知道，所以无论如何我们都不知道碳在哪里
I don't think they knew it so anyway we
don't know where the carbon is in the
单位细胞，所以我们要看看是否可以使用这些峰中的强度数据
unit cells so we're gonna see if we can
use this intensity data from these Peaks
弄清楚在单元格中什么地方通常是我们要去的部分
to figure out where in the unit cell it
is so generally the piece we're going to
感兴趣的是最终变得越来越重要的基本结构因素
be interested in is the basic structure
factor which is which ends up getting
平方，那很好，也许我会在这里首先写出等于
squared and that is well maybe I'll
write this out here first s basis equals
单位单元e中单位单元中的alpha与IG点的总和R alpha乘以B
sum over alpha in the unit cell in unit
cell e to the I G dot R alpha times B
晶胞中有两个原子的alpha，因此此处的s平方为B
alpha for there's two atoms in the unit
cell so s basis squared here will be B
钛加B碳e会写成
titanium plus B carbon e to that will
write it as
2pi HKL点缀在uvw中，然后将其取平方
the 2pi HKL dotted into uvw and then you
take that thing you square it and that
如果您知道这些核素是什么，现在将为您提供基础结构因子
will give you the basis structure factor
now if you knew what these nuclear
散射长度是钛，B是碳，您可能会打架
scattering lengths were be titanium and
B be carbon you might have a fighting
找出紫外线和紫外线的机会，但假设我们不知道可以
chance of figuring out what UV and W
were but suppose we didn't know that can
我们仍然可以取得任何进展，如果我愿意，我们可以取得一些进展
we still make any progress well we can
make a little bit of progress if I give
你的提示，这是你得到的一种提示
you a hint
this is a kind of hint you get on an
考试考试的提示是FCC具有两个原子基础和一个
exam the kind of hint you get on an exam
is that FCC with two atom basis and a
在此基础上，只有两个共同点
basis there's only two common ones only
two common ones common possibilities in
事实上，我什至不知道不是这两种情况之一的任何情况
fact I don't even know of any cases that
are not one of these two there may be
即使是一个定理，你也不能拥有其他任何东西，我不确定
even a theorem that you can't have
anything else I'm not sure about that so
不要引用我，但无论如何，我们都已经看到了这两种可能性
don't quote me but anyway the two
possibilities we both we've seen them
两者之前都存在所谓的锌混合结构
both before there's the so-called zinc
blende structure which is the same as
我们在课堂上讨论过的砷化镓结构将UVW置于
the gallium arsenide structure which we
talked about in class which puts UVW at
一季度，一季度，一季度，另一种可能性
the position one quarter one quarter one
quarter and the other possibility we
还讨论了UVW为1/2 1/2 1/2的氯化钠结构
also discussed is the sodium chloride
structure which has UVW at 1/2 1/2 1/2
那么我们能找出这两种可能性中的哪一种很好吗，让我们
so can we figure out which one of these
two possibilities it is okay well let's
看看我们是否可以这样做，让我们先尝试一下，再尝试锌混合结构好吗
see if we can do it so let's try first
try one try zinc blende structure okay
因此，在这种情况下，基数平方等于B钛加B碳e
so in this case s basis squared equals
well we have B titanium plus B Carbon e
到2 pi H KL，然后是1/4 1/4 1/4
to the 2 pi H KL and then 1/4 1/4 1/4
我们也可以在这里写这个因子这个指数因子也是
which we can also write this factor here
this exponential factor here is also
等价于PI的e乘以I乘以H加k加L或I的两倍
equivalent to e to the PI over two times
I times h plus k plus L or equivalently
这就是我的h加k加L所以好吧，我不在这里了，我们在这里
this would be I to the h plus k plus L
so okay I'm out of room here we're here
所以我们有一个平方的基础等于钛加上碳乘以I到h
so we have s basis squared equals be
titanium plus be carbon times I to the h
加K加l平方好吗，那是h KL的函数
plus K plus l squared okay and what is
that as a function of h KL well there's
三种可能的情况之一我的意思是，情况a是h加
three possibilities
case one I mean a case a is that h plus
k加L是4的倍数，等于整数n的四倍，因此在这种情况下，我们
k plus L is a multiple of 4 equals four
times an integer n so in that case we
获得s的平方的平方等于钛加上碳的绝对值
get s basis squared equals be titanium
plus be carbon the absolute value
平方第二种可能性情况B是
squared the second possibility case B is
h加k加L仍然是偶数，但不是四的倍数，因此我们称
h plus k plus L is still even but it's
not a multiple of four so we'll call for
n加2，在这种情况下，我们得到的s平方等于钛-碳
n plus two in which case we get s basis
squared equals be titanium - be carbon
在第三种情况下平方C是h加k加上L是奇奇在这种情况下S
squared in the third case case C is h
plus k plus L is odd odd in which case S
基数平方是B钛正负I乘以B碳平方，即
basis squared is B titanium plus or
minus I times B Carbon squared which is
钛平方加B碳平方
be titanium squared plus B Carbon
squared
好吧，好吧，让我们凝视一下，您能做什么
good all right so we've let's stare at
that for a second and what can you
从这个井得出结论，无论B钛和B碳有多长
conclude from this well no matter what B
titanium and B carbon are as long as
他们是真实的，他们是三种可能性中最大的一种
they're real which they are the largest
of the three possibilities is always
无论哪种情况，如果它们是钛，都是碳
either case a and
case be if they be titanium be carbon
具有相同的符号，则如果a是三种可能性中的最大值，则
have the same sign then case a is the
largest of the three possibilities if
如果B是三种可能性中的最大值，则它们具有相反的符号，因此
they have opposite sign in case B is the
largest of three possibilities so the
现在，让我们来看看最大的峰肯定是h加k加L
largest Peaks should definitely have
even h plus k plus L now let's look at
这些数据，您将看到h加k加L，您会注意到最高峰
this data and you'll see h plus k plus L
and you'll notice that the highest peaks
总是系统地总是有奇数h加k加l所以总是一个
always have odd h plus k plus l
systematically always there so the one
一一高三一一高三三一高三三
one one is high three one one is high
three three one is high three three
三个很高，其他所有的都很小，所以这并不相同
three is high all the other ones are
small are even so this does not agree
与不同意的数据同意
with the data it does not agree agree
好吧，我们可以尝试其他方法，我们可以尝试氯化钠结构，所以尝试
well we can try something else we can
try the sodium chloride structure so try
氯化钠在这种情况下我们很好我在这里某处写了它
sodium chloride in which case we have
well I wrote it over here somewhere
是的那边是1/2 1/2和1/2所以s的平方是B钛加上
yeah over there it's 1/2 1/2 and 1/2 so
s basis squared is then B titanium plus
B碳乘以e到2 pi HK的碳现在乘以1/2 1/2 1/2，然后全部
B carbon times e to the 2 pi H K now
dotted into 1/2 1/2 1/2 and then all
平方，我们可以重写为B钛加B碳乘以负1/2
squared and that we can rewrite as B
titanium plus B carbon times minus 1/2
h加k加L都平方，所以有两种情况我们可以得到情况1
the h plus k plus L all squared so
there's two cases we can have case 1
好的，所以a是h加k加上L是奇数，在这种情况下，我们有B钛-是
case ok so a is h plus k plus L is odd
in which case we have B titanium - be
碳平方是答案，而案例B案例B是h加k加l等于
carbon squared is the answer whereas
case B case B is h plus k plus l equals
即使在这种情况下，我们有B钛加B碳平方即可
even in which case we have B titanium
plus B Carbon squared ok
那么，现在最大的是什么？您可以看到，如果这个想法
so now what's which one is largest here
well you can see that if this idea maybe
碳具有相同的符号，则偶数将始终更大，而如果它们
carbon have the same sign then the even
will always be larger whereas if they
具有相反的符号，那么如果您查看数据，则奇数会更大
have the opposite sign then the odd will
have larger well if you look at the data
h加k加L奇数显然要大得多，所以这告诉我们
the h plus k plus L odd is clearly much
larger and so that tells us this it's
与这种情况相一致，如果是钛，则钛具有相反的符号
consistent with this case that if be
titanium be titanium has opposite sign
B碳的符号是什么，所以大的峰是B钛-被碳平方
what's its sign of B carbon so the large
Peaks are B titanium - be carbon squared
B钛和B碳具有相反的符号，并且小峰是
with B titanium and B carbon having
opposite sign and the small Peaks are
两者之和也有相反的符号大家好
the sum of the two with them having an
opposite sign as well okay everyone
或多或少有点满意，是的，请说是，好吧，谢谢
happy with that more or less a little
bit yes please say yes all right thank
好的，让我们看看，是的，
you all right
good so let's see so yeah there's the
摘要摘要幻灯片，所以我们得出结论它必须是氯化钠结构
summary summary slide so we conclude it
has to be sodium chloride structure
让我们来看一下，以便我们可以继续讨论哦在这里，让我们讨论一下您
let's see so we can actually go on and
discuss oh here let's discuss how you
产生中子一秒钟，所以我们讨论了您如何产生中子
make neutrons for a second so we
discussed how you make probably make s
我认为上一讲是最后一讲的最后一个托盘，但我们没有讨论
trays in the last in the last last
lecture I think but we haven't discussed
您如何制造中子这是一个中子设施散裂的中子源
how you make neutrons this is a neutron
facility a spallation neutron source
也就在同步加速源旁边的路上
also right down the road next to the
synchrotron source rather large and
昂贵的设备，但我们需要的是需要波长在
expensive apparatus but what we need is
we need neutrons with a wavelength on
一埃的量级如果波长为一，我们如何得到很好的结果
the order of one angstrom how do we get
that well if the wavelength is one
埃的动量是Lambda上的2 pi H bar，据此我们可以计算出
angstrom the momentum is 2 pi H bar over
lambda and from that we can calculate
我们需要的能量在2m上平方P等于大约8000万
that the energy we need is P squared
over 2m equals approximately 80 mil
电子伏特或约800开尔文，我们将适当的因素
electron volts or about 800 Kelvin we
put in the appropriate factor
玻尔兹曼常数使中间温度升高，这可能听起来对您来说
Boltzmann's constant to make an inter
temperature and this might sound to you
就像它很热，但实际上800开尔文对中子来说真的很冷，为什么
like it's hot but in fact 800 Kelvin is
really really cold for neutrons why is
那你如何首先获得中子
that well how do you get the neutrons in
the first place
制造中子使中子恢复到以前没有的状态
making neutrons making neutrons well
back in the old days they didn't have
中子，然后是第二次世界大战和原子弹
neutrons and then along came the the
Second World War and the atomic bomb
项目和原子弹项目之后，他们有核反应堆和
project and after the atomic bomb
project they had nuclear reactors and
核反应堆以中子为副产物，因此可能是副产物
nuclear reactors have neutrons as a
by-product so possibly one is byproduct
裂变，你可以想象，当一个中子从原子核的
of fission and you can imagine that when
a neutron comes off of a of a nucleus in
某些裂变过程产生了数百万个电子伏特
some fission process it's coming out
with millions of electron volts rather
比毫伏电子伏特高得多，所以它非常的有活力
than milla electron volts so it's
extremely extremely energetic so this
800开尔文的能量非常低，还有一种更受欢迎的方法
800 Kelvin is extremely low energy
there's a more favorite method for
因为人们不喜欢在后院安装原子反应堆
making because people don't like to have
atomic reactors in their backyard these
如今，有一种更受青睐的制造中子的方法，实际上它更
days there's a more favored method for
making neutrons in fact it's more
高效的方法也被称为阿巴拉契亚（Appalachia），这就是
efficient method as well which is known
as Appalachia and that's what this
来源是这个中子来源是愿望来源愿望的概念
source is this Neutron source is
aspiration source the idea of aspiration
来源与X射线管的想法没有什么不同，在X射线管中您通常会
source is not unlike the idea of an
x-ray tube where you take usually a
质子和质子，您可以将其加速到大约千兆电子伏特
proton and proton and you accelerate it
to about a Giga electron volt and you
将其击中目标目标，其想法是粉碎一些核和一些核，
hit it onto a target target and the idea
is to smash some nucleus some nuclei and
因为您以如此高的命中率击中中子，所以现在再次开始中子
kick off some neutrons now again since
you're hitting it with such a high a
高能量，您将用一些非常高的能量来启动中子
high energy you're going to kick off
neutrons with some very very high energy
同样，无论您使用哪种方法来产生中子
as well so whichever method you use to
create neutrons they're coming off with
令人难以置信的高能量，您必须将其冷却，以便使其冷却
an incredibly high energy and you have
to make them cold so to make them cold
使用的是主持人，主持人基本上只是一个大坦克
what you use is you use a moderator and
a moderator is basically just a big tank
某些物质，中子可以进入该物质并在附近反弹
of some substance where the neutrons can
go in the substance and bounce around
将能量释放给物质，所以人们经常使用碳石墨
giving off their energy to the substance
so frequently people use carbon graphite
石墨是碳石墨碳水重水许多材料什么
graphite is carbon graphite carbon water
heavy water lots of materials anything
中子可以撞击并释放能量给
that will that the neutrons can bump
into and give off their energy to and
最终在这件事的另一端，你得到了中子，
eventually out the other end of this
thing you get you get neutrons and you
想把它们拉下来，直到我知道
want to
pull them down until they I have about
一旦有中子出来，现在就价值800开尔文的能量
800 Kelvin worth of energy now once you
have the the neutrons coming out you
需要以某种方式弄清楚如何使它们单色八
need to somehow figure out how to make
them monochromatic monochrome eight
意味着您只想获得一个波长传闻，这是第一个规则
meaning you just want to get one
wavelength rumor that is the first rule
没有您的波长，所以您必须要单色八倍，所以您如何
no your wavelength so you have to
monochrome eight so how do you
单色八种方法之一是衍射，因此可以使用晶体
monochrome eight one way method one is
to diffract so you can use a crystal
众所周知，我们在x射线以及来自
that's known we mentioned this in the
case of x-rays as well diffract from a
已知晶体中的已知晶体，有时可以起作用，但是还有另一个
known crystal from known crystal and
that sometimes works but there's another
也使用的方法对中子非常好
method which is also used which is very
nice for neutrons which is a
飞行时间方法飞行时间以下列方式工作
time-of-flight method time-of-flight
which works in the following way
所以你有一束中子进入这里，然后你会有一个
so you have a beam of neutrons coming in
over here and then you have sort of a
您可以打开和关闭的窗口打开并关闭您想要的任何东西，然后您
window which you can open and close open
and close whatever you want and then you
从这里到这里有一个长距离的el，另一个可以打开的窗口
have a long spacing el from here to here
and another window which you can open
然后关闭，所以您可以快速打开和关闭窗口
and close so you open up and close the
window very quickly to let in a little
脉冲中子，然后在某个时间点T后再打开另一个
pulse of neutrons and then at some time
delta T later you open up the other
窗口，所以您知道L，您知道T，所以如果它是从第一个窗口到
window so then you know L you know T so
if it made it from the first window to
ΔT中的第二个窗口你知道它的速度，所以L除以ΔT是
the second window in delta T you know
its velocity so L divided by delta T is
如果知道它的速度，就知道它的动量。
its velocity if you know its velocity
you know its momentum if you know its
动量，您知道它的波长，所以您可以通过给它一个
momentum you know its wavelength so you
can select by knowing how by giving it a
从第一个窗口到第二个窗口需要一定的时间
certain amount of time to get from the
first window to the second window you
可以为那里的特定速度选择特定的速度
can select for a particular velocity
there for a particular momentum there
对于特定的波长，我还要提及的一件事是
for a particular wavelength one more
thing that I do want to mention about
在接下来的中子中，中子只会说一两件事
neutrons will say maybe just one or two
more things about them in the next
讲座，但我现在想提一提，这是人们喜欢中子的原因之一
lecture but I do want to mention now is
one of the reasons people like neutrons
是中子实际上有一个自旋，它使您能够看到具有
is the neutrons actually have a spin and
that enables you to see things that have
如果在一个区域中有更多旋转，则旋转很重要的重要性
importance where the spin is important
if you have more spins in one region
而不是另一个区域，中子对它们感到
than another region the neutrons are
sensitive to that they feel the the
作为光子不存在的潜力的局部磁环境
local magnetic environment as a
potential where as photons do not they
不在乎中子在当地的磁场环境，因为
don't care about the local
magnetic environment neutrons do because
中子有一些自旋，我们会停在那儿，然后我们将完成
the neutrons have some spin okay we'll
stop there and we'll pick up finish this
下一场下一场演讲[掌声]
off next next lecture
[Applause]